Imagine, you are working seriously
with ChatGPT, and your code is
almost complete, and your prompts
are crafted beautifully,
and ChatGPT is about to complete
your task, but boom!
At the same time, ChatGPT stopped
responding to you.
Have you ever noticed this?
And why is it not responding?
Because of something called as Rate
Limiting.
You have reached the current usage
cap for the ChatGPT 4.0.
Try again in 4 hours.
This is not only in ChatGPT,
guys.
When you are using Claude Code,
you have faced that too?
Message limit reached,
resets at 8.30 pm, and maybe in
Cursor, and also in GitHub Copilot.
This is not only in ChatGPT,
Claude, Cursor, or GitHub.
Not only that, if you are using any
kind of LLM tools or AI tools,
every single tool has these limits.
And how do you calculate these
limits?
There is no magic behind it,
and the single term that defines
these limits are called tokens.
What are tokens?
How do you calculate tokens?
Every single thing we will learn in
this video.
And literally, there are a couple of
developers who don't even understand
what tokens are.
So, I am making this video to help
you understand what tokens are
visually.
So, by the end of this video,
what you will understand is why some
AI tools have limits,
and why long prompts cost you more,
and also why ChatGPT forgets your
old context,
and why answers cost you more than
the prompts.
And in all the questions,
I will also explain two technical
terms, which are TPS, tokens per
second,
and also the context window.
If you remember, in our previous
video, when we are hitting ChatGPT
API,
in the output response,
we have something called as prompt
tokens, completion tokens,
and total tokens.
We didn't cover this part in the
last video.
But by the end of this video,
you will be also able to understand
these terms as well.
So, before we understand what tokens
are, think about one question.
When you go to ChatGPT and type
hello, do you think ChatGPT will
be able to understand hello?
H -E -L -L -O?
No, because it is a machine,
right?
Machine doesn't understand Telugu,
Hindi, English, it is not a human.
It doesn't have intelligence like
human.
But if the machine doesn't
understand the hello text,
how is it able to interpret our
meaning?
Yeah?
Think about it.
So fundamentally, machines work
based on mathematics.
So, you need to have mathematical
operations to be done.
If you say hello, you can't do any
mathematical operations on hello.
But if I can convert hello into
something like numbers,
I can do mathematical operations on
numbers, right?
So, whenever you are putting some
text to any of these LLMs,
ChatGPT, Gemini, Claude,
or internally, all of these texts
will be converted into numbers.
Now, you might have a question in
your brain.
How do we convert these texts into
numbers?
That's an interesting question.
So, if you are coming from a
programming background,
you already know what is called
ASCII numbers.
What is ASCII numbers?
Very simple thing.
In our alphabets, we assign a
dedicated number to every alphabet.
So, capital A is 65.
Capital B is 66.
Small a is 97.
Like this, we will assign a
dedicated number to every alphabet.
Now, what is our initial question?
Hello, right?
So, we will split this into letters.
H, E, L, L, O.
And what is the number H?
Let's assume 104.
And E is 101.
And L is 108.
And O is 111.
Now, I can convert the word Hello
into a vector of these numbers.
Isn't it?
So, Hello is converted like this.
Now, ChatGPT will be able to
understand Hello.
Yes, absolutely.
And I can convert Hi.
I can convert Bye.
I can convert any of these things by
converting it into characters.
Let's take a moment and think about
it, guys.
By doing this, is it a good thing or
is it a bad thing?
Think about it.
I will wait like 10 seconds.
So, by writing the text in this
numerical representation,
there is one fundamental problem.
What is that fundamental problem?
When you convert into Hi and Hello,
there is no link between the two
output numbers.
That is, a machine will not be able
to understand the meaning of Hi and
Hello by looking at these numbers.
So, that is where the intelligence
happens.
How do we humans work?
We think about Hi or Hello in a
similar context.
But how does a machine understand
that context?
If we can convert these numbers into
a specific standard format.
So, this is the fundamental problem
that you will face when you are
converting your text into numbers
using ASCII number patterns.
But ChatGPT is doing something more
powerful.
It understands patterns,
meanings, relationships.
So, what do we understand?
We need something that not only
stores the numbers, but we also need
to retain the relationships,
context and meaning.
So, we understood that ASCII does
not work.
So, what is the other pattern?
And that is where Transformers and
Embeddings come into picture.
Do not worry.
We will not go into Transformers and
Embeddings in detail in this video.
We will touch at a high level.
So, now let us understand what a
token is.
This is the important stuff.
A token is a small piece of text.
The model reads before it turns that
piece into a number.
Why did we do this?
For the model to understand,
we need to convert our text into
number.
But in the process, there is one
more step and that step is called
tokenization or a token.
We have a simple word called Hello.
Hello is a simple word.
So, Hello is just a one token and we
will convert that token into this
number using something called as
Embeddings.
What does Embeddings mean?
We will learn in the next section.
So, just wait a minute.
And we have another word which is
Hello space question mark.
Look here, specifically Hello space
and question mark.
And when we convert that into
tokens, it is classified into three
tokens.
Hello is token one, space is token
two and question mark is token
three.
And let's say we have a bigger word.
I mean, I am not sure what this is.
But when there are big words like
this, the model will not be able to
understand this.
Because tomorrow, what if there are
new words?
What will prompt
engineering do when there are new
words?
The model will not be able to
understand, right?
So, that is why they use something
called as tokenization.
They convert the word into the root
word, very small small chunks.
This entire word, it will be split
into antidisestablishment
arianism.
So, like this, a single word can be
converted into one, two,
three, four, five, six tokens.
Look here, this is a single word,
but it only takes one token.
But this is a single word,
but it took six tokens.
And let's take one more example.
I love mangoes dot.
Even the punctuations will also take
place in the tokenization.
So, I is a token, love is a token,
mango is a token.
Look at this.
Mangoes is converting into a root
word.
Mango, play, played, place.
So, like this, yes, is a separate
token and dot is a separate token.
So, a sentence means you are
converting into tokens.
So, what are tokens?
We have a big sentence.
You are breaking that into smaller
smaller chunks.
And that chunks are called tokens.
And now we have tokens.
What is the logical next step?
To convert each of these tokens into
numbers.
And how do we convert those numbers?
Using a technique called embedding.
Embedding simply means,
very simply,
It is a way to convert your
tokens into a vector or numerical
representation.
Now, what is the difference between
the ASCII we did earlier?
When you convert using embedding
techniques,
you will find all of the similar
products or similar text in a
similar region.
Let's say,
I converted
into these kind of vectors for three
fruits, mango, apple, banana.
And these vectors are in a very
similar space.
They are not closely related with
car, train or bus.
All of these are in a closed space.
All of these are in another closed
space.
So, here you are converting the text
into vectors.
And that vectors are giving some
meaning to it based on the meaning
of the words.
Because they are closely related.
And that is how model understands,
Hello and Hi are very similar
because their vector representations
are very close to each other.
If you want detailed video on
embeddings, please let me know in
the comment section below.
And one more thing, there are
different types of embedding
techniques.
You may ask, why mango has such a
big vector representation?
There are a couple of embedding
techniques where for every word you
get 1024 dimensions.
That means, for every word you will
get 1024 length vector.
So, it depends on the model,
on the context, which kind of
embedding model you need to use.
You need to change all of those
things.
But that is for a later video.
Now, what we are going to do is,
we will look at how OpenAI will
convert the words into numbers.
This is from the OpenAI website,
Tokenizer.
Now, let's say, I will put Hello
here.
Now, if our input text is Hello,
it is just only one token and five
characters.
And Hello is in a single color code.
That means, it is a single token.
And when you change it to this token
ID, it is where it is converting the
Hello token into a number.
So, what does Hello do?
It does 24912.
What if I will put capital Hello?
When you even change caps lock,
that token number is going to
change.
The token ID is going to change.
And this token ID will change based
on different types of models that
you use.
If you put GPT 4 or GPT 3.5,
it is giving token ID as 9906.
But if you put GPT 5, it is 13225.
So, every model follows their own
type of embedding techniques.
We will learn in the later parts of
the videos, not in this video.
And if you take GPT 3,
it is 15496.
Now, let's take one more example.
I love mangoes.
Look here.
I love mangoes, if I put it here.
I is a token. Love is a token.
Because I gave M small letter and
gave the rest to different people.
It is breaking into multiple tokens.
I love mangoes because of the way
that I write, it is occupying six
tokens.
But now what I will do is,
I will just put this in a single
word, mangoes.
Look here.
It is taking five tokens.
So, if you make a spelling mistake,
you are using more tokens.
Isn't it?
And I can get the token IDs for
every word.
Maybe let's take this paragraph
right here and let's put it here.
And look here.
When I put text, if is a token,
you is a token.
And there is a word programmatic.
It is broken down into two things.
Programmatic.
So, our big words are the same.
All of them are broken down into
smaller words called tokens.
And for every smaller word token,
you are converting into a number
using a technique called embedding.
And that ID is called a token ID.
So, based on the text that you
write, you are deciding how many
tokens you are using.
Even the spaces, punctuations,
emojis, every single thing contains
the tokens.
If you use it in Telugu,
Hindi or English, you are going to
consume more amount of tokens.
I will show it to you live in this
right now.
So, what we are going to do is,
let's open translate.
I will put English to Telugu.
And here we will put hello.
And hello is an English word.
If I take it here and if I put it
here, it is only one token.
But if I copy the same hello in
Telugu, if I put it here,
it is occupying nine tokens.
That means, if you do the same
communication in English,
you are going to consume one token.
But the same thing, if you do it in
Telugu, you are going to consume
nine tokens.
Why? Because models are designed
that way.
And look at the token IDs.
Look, all the tokens have come to
hello.
But if I put it in English,
it is just one token ID.
Isn't it interesting?
That is why without you knowing,
you are consuming more amount of
tokens.
And that is why you are hitting your
limits.
And there are different types of
tokens, guys.
Input tokens and output tokens.
But before that, let us understand
one simple thing.
You put an input to ChatGPT and
you get output.
So, what is the thing that is
happening in the background?
My input is converted into tokens.
And these tokens are getting
converted into embeddings.
And these embeddings will go into
ChatGPT.
And in ChatGPT, they will process
all of these embeddings.
And they will try to generate output
embeddings.
And these embeddings, they will
generate it back into tokens.
And they will convert these tokens
back into the output.
When you give a prompt,
all of this entire process is going
to happen in the back end.
So, in such a case, you might notice
a couple of things.
Sometimes, ChatGPT will give you
the answers instantly.
Sometimes, it will take some time
and give you the response.
So, why?
That is where we learn about a
concept called TPS, which is
called Tokens Per Second.
What does this mean?
What is the capability of the LLM
model to generate how many number of
tokens that it can generate in a
second?
How many tokens can be generated in
a second?
Based on that, you will see some
response.
Sometimes it is fast, sometimes it
is slow.
If it generates more, it feels fast.
If it generates less, it is slow.
And how does this fast and slow
depend?
Based on your complexity of the
question, based on the server's
busyness, based on the prompt that
you provide, based on the thinking
model, reasoning capacity.
So, based on all these,
your output will depend on TPS.
You might have heard this word
before.
So, when you try to download free or
open source models, you always check
about what is TPS.
If the TPS is very low,
you will see that the model is
lagging a lot.
If the TPS is very high,
you will feel that the model is
working blazingly fast.
And now the interesting part,
which is the cost.
Every token that you send is getting
billed.
That is for sure.
So, all these LLM models,
OpenAI, ChatGPT, Grok,
Claude, all of these things will work
based on the tokens.
Depending on the number of tokens
you send, they will get billed.
So, let us say, for example,
there is a ChatGPT 5.5 model.
So, for every million tokens that
you send as an input, it is going to
charge you $5.
That is a good amount.
For every million tokens,
it is only $5.
But that is on the input side.
When you think about the output,
it is going to charge you $30 per
million tokens, which is almost 6X
the price.
Why?
Input is basically your question.
It is not using any kind of
processing or intelligence.
But when you send a question to
ChatGPT, to generate an answer,
it is going to use a lot of
resources.
And that is why output token cost is
almost higher than the input token
cost.
And for GPT 5.4, $2.5 per million
tokens and $15 per million tokens
for output.
And Claude Opus 4.7, $5 per million
tokens in the input and $25 per
million tokens in the output.
And obviously, prices change with a
lot of time.
Maybe the price might have already
changed.
So always check the official API
documentation for the price list.
This is just to give you an
observation of how input and output
tokens will cost you.
And why output is always almost 4 to
5 times costlier than the input
tokens.
And obviously, when you are using
open source models like LLaMA or LLaMA
3.3, everything is free.
Because you will download the whole
model and you are not going to pay
any price for these things.
And the next important phase,
which is called the hidden tax.
You might think that now you got the
understanding of what tokens are and
I can calculate how many tokens that
I am using.
But no, that is not the one that is
going to work in the real time.
Because now if you think about
agents or LLMs, they have
capabilities like tools.
MCPs, skills, markdown files,
dot MD, memory, a lot of stuff and
conversation history.
So now when you are working in a
Codex or in Claude, you are going
to use a lot of prompts.
And with every prompt,
you are not only just sending your
questions, you are also sending what
is your prompt, what is your
context, what are your files.
And then tool definitions,
MCPs, past conversations,
they will calculate tokens.
You are not only sending your single
question, you are sending all the
information regarding all of the
capabilities.
And every time
you are sending a question,
so when you say hi, it is not only
just taking it as a hi,
it is taking with a lot of different
different information guys.
So that is why it
is going to consume a lot and I
will also show you the breakdown on
the screen itself right now.
And the next and the last one,
which is called a context window.
Context window means like us humans,
LLMs have a limited capacity in the
brain.
They can only understand some part
of text, maybe let us say one book.
They can only understand one book at
a time.
That is what we call it as a context
window.
Every model has their own context
Some models have 1 million context
window, 2 million context window.
What does that mean?
The number of tokens that you can
send or memorize in a single
session.
That is what we call it as a
context.
For example, for GPT 3.5,
it can only hold maybe 32 pages of a
book.
And Gemini 1.5 Pro can capture 4000
pages of a book.
So every model has its own context
and you need to go to their API
documentation phase
to understand what are the limits
and context for every model.
Let us say you are
sending a lot of text and you are
sending and filling up the tokens.
And once you fill up these tokens,
let us say like this.
At the end, once the context is
full, the usage limit will also
increase.
And that is why your AI tools will
not remember the past context.
Because you start filling up the
memory brain.
After one point, these points they
will forget.
So it is recommended to start new
chats often.
And do not paste huge files
unnecessarily because you are
consuming a lot of context.
And then use cheap models for
smaller tasks and tell the AI to be
concise.
And that is everything you need to
know regarding tokens.
And if you learned something from
this video, please let me know in
the comment section below.
And if you know someone who might
need this video, please share it
across.
If you are a student, please share
it in the college group so that
other people can also learn from
these videos.
Thank you. Bye bye.